<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<huntevents>
    <event name="Broken Lanterns" number="1">
        <text>The survivors feel something crunching beneath their feet. The event revealer may choose to lower their lantern and investigate or ignore the sensation and continue their journey. If they choose to investigate, the event revealer gains +1 courage and rolls 1d10. Otherwise, roll again on the hunt event table before moving on the hunt event board.</text>
        <investigae>true</investigae>
        <rolltable>
            <roll min="1" max="5">You fumble and cut your foot on a jagged shard. Suffer monster level event damage to your legs.</roll>
            <roll min="6" max="8">You salvage something usefu. Gain 1 broken lantern basic resource.</roll>
            <roll min="9" max="+">The survivors uncover a long-abandoned lantern hoard. The forlorn sight fills them with drea, each survivor sets their insanity to 0. After composing themselves, each survivor scavenges 1 broken lantern basic resource; add them to the settlement storage.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Corpse" number="2">
        <text>The survivors are overcome by a sudden chill, their breath seizing in their lungs. The survivors' teeth chatter mercilessly. All survivors lose monster level survival. At the center of the sudden frost is a perfectly preserved corpse.\nIf the settlement has Cannibalize, the event revealer gains 1 random basic resource.\nIf the settlement has Graves, the event revealer examines the corpse and gains +1 courage and +1 understanding.\nIf the settlement has Momento Mori, the event revealer understands a little about what happened to the corpse. They gain 1 random fighting art.</text>
    </event>
    <event name="Cance Pigeons" number="3">
        <text>The survivors are surrounded by the echoing coo of infant babble. Strange bab-faced birds circle overhead. Gripped with instinctual horror, the survivors break into a run! Each survivor rolls 1d10. The lowest scoring survivor (or survivors, in case of ties) becomes a straggler. If any survivor has noisy gear, -2 to their roll. Each straggler rolls 1d10. If any survivor has a whip, they crack it, scattering many of the birds. Each straggler adds +4 to their roll.</text>
        <stragglere>true</stragglere>
        <rolltable>
            <roll min="1" max="3">Running and flailing wildly, you suddenly find yourself panicked and alone. The waiting cancer pigeons descend and mercilessly peck your back, their happy cooing filling your head with horror. An hour later, the other survivors find you balled up and weeping on the ground. You are Dead Inside: you cannot gain survival. Record this impairment.</roll>
            <roll min="4" max="6">A cancer pigeon latches onto your back! Shake it free by spending 1 survival. Otherwise, you are Dead Inside: you cannot gain survival. Record this impariment.</roll>
            <roll min="7" max="8">You escape the terrible creatures.</roll>
            <roll min="9" max="+">You manage to strike one of the foul creatures down. Gain 1 random basic resource.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Famine" number="4">
        <text>The path ahead is arid and dead. You may have survivors gain +1 courage and press on. Otherwise, roll again on the hunt event table before moving on the hunt board. If you press on, your stomachs grumble in the dark as you stumble forward. The survivors pool their supplies. The event reavealer rolls 1d10 and adds +2 to their roll for each consumable gear or resource the group has.</text>
        <rolltable>
            <roll min="1" max="8">The hunt takes its toll. Powerful hunger pangs set in. All survivors gain -1 speed token.</roll>
            <roll min="9" max="14">You manage to stave off the terrible hunger.</roll>
            <roll min="15" max="+">Everyone is invigorate by their snack. Each suvivor gains +1 survival.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Flesh Fields" number="5">
        <text>Ahead, the stone faces on the ground give way to a field of man-sized, fleshy boils sprouting thick black hair. The sinuous terrain radiates moist heat. As they travel, every survivor suffers heat exhaustion, losing 1 survival. The event revealer rolls 1d10. If any survivor has a sickle, they help clear a path by cutting back the thick, black hair. Add +4 to your roll.</text>
        <rolltable>
            <roll min="1" max="1">The event revealer contracts a flesh-eating disease brushing past the giant boils! A random limb is affected and must be amputated immediately! Roll 1d10, 1-5: arms, 6-10: legs. Suffer the dismembered severe injury at this location.</roll>
            <roll min="2" max="3">If any survivor is insane, they imagine the flesh fields are attacking! They become hysterical, flailing and tangling themselves in the thick hair. Each insane survivor suffers monster level event damage to a random location.</roll>
            <roll min="4" max="7">It's hot and gross, but the survivors pass through the flesh fields with no complications.</roll>
            <roll min="8" max="9">The event revealer makes the best of a bad situation and cuts a portion of the flesh free. GAin 1 hide basic resource.</roll>
            <roll min="10" max="+">Each survivor harvest 1 hide basic resource from the flesh fields.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Faceless Statue" number="6">
        <text>The survivors come upon a faceless statue holding a shining lanter. Basking in the warm light, the survivors are renewed. Each survivors gains 1 survival.\nIf the settlement has Sculpture, the survivors deeply appreciate the artist's suble craftsmanship. Each survivor rolls 1d10. Gain that many survival and +1 understanding.\nThe survivors may rest here longer. If they do, each survivor heals all injurl levels and lost armor points on 1 hit location. However, they lose track of their quarry. Move it 1 space away from the survivors on the hunt board. If a survivor heals more than 5 lost armor points this way, they stare into the shining light for too long and gain 1 random disorder,\n If all survivors are insane, they cannot rest longer.</text>
    </event>
    <event name="Hungry Ground" number="7">
        <text>The ground suddenly splits and a gaping stone mouth attempts to devour the event revealer whole! The event revealer rolls 1d10.\nIf another survivor has a whip, they throw a line to the event revealer. Add +4 to your roll.</text>
        <rolltable>
            <roll min="1" max="1">With a muffled scream, you disappear into the ground. You manage to grab hold of a precarious ledge above the gaping maw. Lose all survival as you desperately climb up to safety. If you had none, you fall. Bones crunch between stone teeth. You are devoured whole. Dead.</roll>
            <roll min="2" max="5">You scramble, but your leg is caught in the terrible maw. Suffer 2 event damage to the legs.</roll>
            <roll min="6" max="9">You manage to leap away in time!</roll>
            <roll min="10" max="+">Burp! Gurgle! The floor vomits a shiny pieve of scrap. Gain 1 broken lantern basic resource.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Wailing Smoke" number="8">
        <text>A constant moan follows the survivors. Eventually, they enter a area shrouded in thick fog and the wailing reaches a fevered pitch.\nEvery non-deaf survivor rolls 1d1-. If all survivors are deaf, they continue alon, heedless to the cacophony: end this event. The lowest scoring survivor (or survivors, in case of ties) becomes a straggler. EachStraggler rolls 1d10. If any survivor has noisy gear, the straggler adds +2 to their roll.\nIf any survivor has noisy gear and the settlement has Drums, they counter the wails with a tune from home. Do not roll on the table and each survivor gains +2 insanity and +2 survival.</text>
        <rolltable>
            <roll min="1" max="3">The fod around you turns black and fills with shapes of tormented faces. You are driven to madness. Gain 1 random disorder.</roll>
            <roll min="4" max="6">The fog grows soupy and begins to wail. You plug your ears with your fingers, but it's hopeless. Suffer monster level brain event damage.</roll>
            <roll min="7" max="9">You stick your thumbs into your ear and break into a run, leaving the wailing smoke.</roll>
            <roll min="10" max="+">Mimicking the disturbing smoke, you calmly start to wail with it. Gain +2 insanity.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Golden Light" number="9">
        <text>A golden light blinds the survivors, stopping them in their tracks. The light shines from a single source. The event revealer is compelled to investigate. They gain +1 courage and roll 1d10.\nIf the event revealer is blind, they walk in the wrong direction and gain +3 insanity. Roll again on the hunt event table and do not investigate the light.</text>
        <rolltable>
            <roll min="1" max="3">The light is overpowering. Your fragile mind cannot understand its soundless words. GAin 1 random disorder.</roll>
            <roll min="4" max="8">You wander through the light, bathed in a warm, awful feeling. You don't find anything other than exposure. Suffer monster level event damage to a random hit location.</roll>
            <roll min="9" max="+">Something about the light stirs you, and your resolve intensifies. Gain +1 survival.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Harvester" number="10">
        <text>This event cannot be rerolled or avoided in any way. The ground quakes and cracks beneath the survivors. A colossal worm bursts from below, its skin a mosaic of screaming faces. The mere sight of it is maddening.\nAll survivors gain 1 random disorder and must spend 1 survival or be devoured whole. If any survivor has noisy gear, the Harvester is drawn to the sound and they are instantly devoured. Nothing can save them.\nThe creature is so horrifying that the survivors' brains erase the experience from their memories. Do not gain the benefits of your death principle.</text>
    </event>
    <event name="Monster Droppings" number="11">
        <text>The survivors find some monster droppings, like those of their quarry. The event revealer chooses to either investigate or consume the droppings (choose only one).\nIf the event revealer investigates, gain +1 understanding and roll 1d10.\nIf the event revealer consumes, gain +1 courage and roll 1d10.</text>
        <rolltable type="Investigate" person="Event Revealer">
            <roll min="1" max="3">You discover just how sickening playing with feces is. Lose 1 survival and roll again on the hunt event table before moving on the hunt board.</roll>
            <roll min="4" max="6">The droppings tell a story. You are on the right track. Gain +1 survival.</roll>
            <roll min="7" max="+">You know these droppings well. You may skip the next hunt space. If this move begins the showdown, the survivors ambush their quarry.</roll>
        </rolltable>
        <rolltable type="Consume" person="Event Revealer">
            <roll min="1" max="3">It seems you weren't the only one with this idea! You attempt to cough out the refuse, but your mouth is full of wriggling parasites! They borrow upwards through your nasal cavity into your brain. From now on, you always feel slightly dizzy. Suffer -1 permanent evasion.\nIn addition, if you have the Quixotic disorder, the parasites savor the unique neural activity of your brain, feeing relentlessly and excreting waste which further fuels your madness. Gain +10 insanity and the Immortal disorder. Your Quixotic disorder can never be removed for any reason.</roll>
            <roll min="4" max="6">It's repulsive. Your title becomes "Scat Man". Everyone in the settlement must call you by that name from now on.</roll>
            <roll min="7" max="+">There was something quite special about the feces. Gain +1 speed and +1 strength token.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Destiny-Bound" number="12">
        <text>The survivors collectively feel a heightened level of anticipation. Their goal is close at hand. The event revealer gains +1 courage! The survivors may skip the next hunt space. If this movement starts the showdown, the survivors ambush their quarry.</text>
    </event>
    <event name="Overload" number="13">
        <text>The event revealer falls to their knees, sobbing uncontrollably. They've simply had too much. They lose d10 survival and gain 1 random disorder.\nIf the settlement has Accept Darkness, the event revealer embraces their despair. Roll 1d10.\nIf the settlement has Collective Toil, they slowly pull themselves to their feet, promising to never give up hope. Roll 1d10.</text>
        <rolltable person="Event Revealer">
            <roll min="1" max="5">The depths of your misery are deeper than you could have ever imagined. Gain disorders until you have 3 of them. Lose all survival.</roll>
            <roll min="6" max="+">You sink to the bottom of your misery then scrape its very foundations, hungry for more! You uncover a primal rage surrounding a core of serene calm. Gain +1 understanding and the Rageholic disorder.</roll>
        </rolltable>
        <rolltable person="Event Revealer">
            <roll min="1" max="5">You rise, silent tear streaming down your face. With the settlement at your back, you are ready to face the darkness. Gain +1 courage and +1d10 survival.</roll>
            <roll min="6" max="+">You briefly touch the bottom of your misery and return to full awareness with new experiences to share. If any survivors return to the settlement this year, gain +2 endeavors</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Chance Encounter" number="14">
        <text>The survivors encounter a bewitching, barefoot waif with soot-covered feet. If you already rolled this event on this hunt, or if all survivors are insane, she turns her back and disappeas into the darkness. Roll again on the hunt event table before moving on the hunt board.\nOtherwise, exclaiming wildly at the survivors, the woman's presence fills everyone with the alien feeling of hope. All survivors gain +1 courage, +1 understanding.\nIf the settlement has Hovel, she snaps her fingers and ages before your eyes! A chill passes over the survivors. Their bodies and armor spontaneously knit themselves back together. Heal all injury levels and lost armor points. Then, she pulls a random survivor aside and whipsers secrets of the upcoming hunt. They gain +1 accuracy token.</text>
    </event>
    <event name="Man-Trap" number="15">
        <text>The event revealer springs a terrible trap! Roll 1d10.</text>
        <rolltable person="Event Revealer">
            <roll min="1" max="2">With a terrible crash, the steel jaws of the man-trap cleanly sever your foot. Suffer the dismembered leg severe injury.</roll>
            <roll min="3" max="6">Mangled leg. Destrol all armor at the legs location, then suffer 1 event damage to the legs.</roll>
            <roll min="7" max="9">The trap is quite old and wak. Suffer 1 event damage to the legs.</roll>
            <roll min="10" max="+">The event revealer's foot knocks into the trap, giving everyone a scare! However, it was already sprung, leaving an unfortunate prize in its jaws. Gain 1 random basic resource.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Night Terrors" number="16">
        <text>Your miserable sleep is plagued with mind-bending nightmares. Each survivor rolls 1d10. If the result is greater than their insanity, they learn something from the waking horror and gain +1 understanding. Otherwise, they gain 1 random disorder.&#xD;&#xA;If any survivor is a savior or has the Extra Sense fighting art, they disappear into the dream, emerging from the darkness hours late. They gain +4 Hunt XP and a random basic resource.</text>
    </event>
    <event name="Face-to-Face" number="17">
        <text>Amidst the sea of stone faces, one catches the event revealer's eye. They feel compelled to investigate. Gain +1 courage and roll 1d10.</text>
        <rolltable person="Event Revealer" type="Investigate">
            <roll min="1" max="1">The face is identical to your own. Spend 1d5 survival or reduce your understanding to 0.</roll>
            <roll min="2" max="7">The face reminds you of someone dear. Your heart aches with loneliness. If your survival is greater than your insanity, suffer monster level brain event damage.</roll>
            <roll min="8" max="+">The face is your own but older and wiser. Gain +1 survival and +1 understanding.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Dead Weed" number="18">
        <text>You find a strange plant growing from the eyes of a stone face. The event revealer tries to harvest it. Roll 1d10. If any survivor has a sickle, add +4 to their roll.</text>
        <rolltable person="Event Revealer">
            <roll min="1" max="7">Try as you might, you cannot pull out the deeply rooted weed.</roll>
            <roll min="8" max="+">You pull the weed free! It has enourmous regenerative power. Each survivor rubs it on their skin and removes 1 permanent severe injur. Then it crumbles into dust in your hands.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Exhalation of Darkness" number="19">
        <text>The survivors are enveloped in a steamy darkness that dims their lantern lights. They become separated from each other and hopelessly lost. If a survivor has the Leader fighting art, they boldly stride into the clammy darkness and gather everyone. Otherwise, each survivor rolls 1d10. The lowest scoring survivor (or survivors, in case of ties) becomes a straggler. Each straggler rolls 1d10.</text>
        <rolltable person="Straggler">
            <roll min="1" max="2">You trip and fall into the bones of an ancient monster, smashing a piece of gear on the way down. Archive 1 gear of your choice from your gear grid.</roll>
            <roll min="3" max="5">Something unseen attacks you, suffer 1 brain event damage and 1 event damage to a random location.</roll>
            <roll min="6" max="8">You bang into a giant stone face's nose! Suffer 1 head event damage.</roll>
            <roll min="9" max="+">You're not sure how, but you leave the darkness with your hands full. Gain 1 random basic resource.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Dry Lands" number="20">
        <text>As the survivors press forward, the air turns dry and the ground cracks. The survivors suffer heat exhaustion. Each survivor loses 1 survivoal. If they are wearing fur or heavy gear, they instead lose d5 survival.&#xD;&#xA;If any survivor has a pickaxe, the survivors break open an interesting-looking veing in the cracked ground. Gain 1 Iron strange resource.</text>
    </event>
    <event name="Drawings" number="21">
        <text>Cowering in a cave, the survivors find strange drawings decorating the walls. They appear to contain a message. Any survivor with 3+ understanding may try to decipher the drawings by rolling 1d10. If the settlement has Pictographs, every survivor may roll (regardless of their understanding) and add +4 to their rolls.</text>
        <rolltable person="Any Survivor with 3+ understanding">
            <roll min="1" max="3">Your nose begins to bleed. Suffer monster level brain event damage.</roll>
            <roll min="4" max="7">The true meaning escapes you. Gain +1 insanity.</roll>
            <roll min="8" max="+">The drawings teach you a new way to fight monsters! Gain +2 survival and a random fighting art.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Acid Rain" number="22">
        <text>The darkness above is suddenly alight with a storm of acid rain. It smells terrible, burns flesh, and forms hissing pools in the upturned mouths of the stone faces. All survivors suffer monster level event damage to every hit location as they scamble to find shelter.&#xD;&#xA;If the settlement has Sculpture, the survivors silently watch the storm erode the stone faces, erasing their features. They wonder exactly who or what repairs the broken faces, if there is such a thing. The survivors share a dark laugh, each gaining monster level survival.&#xD;&#xA;Roll 1d10. On a 6+ the storm moves homeward. Add the Acid Storm settlement event to the timeline next year.</text>
    </event>
    <event name="Clean Water" number="23">
        <text>The survivors pass a forlorn fountain in the shape of a lion's face. A stream of crystal-clear water flows from its mouth. Each survivor consumes the water, gaining +1 survival and +1 courage. Any number of survivors may douse their head in the water and roll 1d10.</text>
        <rolltable person="Any Survivor">
            <roll min="1" max="2">The instant it becomes wet, your hair turns stark white. Gain 1 random disorder.</roll>
            <roll min="3" max="5">Your hair is wet. Congratulations.</roll>
            <roll min="6" max="8">The water is bracing. Gain +1 understanding or remove a disorder of your choice.</roll>
            <roll min="9" max="+">The water is shockingly cold! It rushes over you like a tidal wave and leaves you awestruck. Set your insanity to 0 and remove all disorders.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Food from the Mouths of Oters" number="24">
        <text>The survivors pass a stone face that appears to be holding something in its mouth. The event revealer investigates. Gain +1 courage and roll 1d10.</text>
        <rolltable person="Event Revealer" type="Investigate">
            <roll min="1" max="2">You yell out in pain and pull your hand back, revealing a bloody gash. Did the stone face just bite? Suffer monster level brain event damage and monster level event arm damage.</roll>
            <roll min="3" max="5">There's nothing. It was just a trick of the lantern light.</roll>
            <roll min="6" max="8">More rocks, what did you expect? Gain 1 Founding Stone starting gear.</roll>
            <roll min="9" max="+">You pull out a masticated mass. Gain 1 random basic resource and 2 insanity.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Titans in the Dark" number="25">
        <text>An earsplitting bellow marks the passing of a truly titanic beast. All non-deaf survivors suffer monster level brain event damage. The survivors cower on the ground, lying as lfat as possible and hoping they are simply to small to be worth eating.&#xD;&#xA;Each survivor rolls 1d10. The lowest scoring survivor (or survivors, in case of ties) becomes a straggler. If any survivor has noisy gear, -2 to their roll. &#xD;&#xA;Each straggler rolls 1d10.</text>
        <rolltable person="Straggler">
            <roll min="1" max="1">You're plucked from the ground and eaten whole. Dead. If the settlement has Survival of the Fittest, you twist out of its mouth and land with a thud. Suffer the broken arm and broken leg severe injuries but do not die.</roll>
            <roll min="2" max="4">Something snatches you in its great maw and chews you for 1 event damage to 1d5 random hit locations.</roll>
            <roll min="5" max="6">The clamping jaws barely nip you! Suffer monster level event damage to a random hit location.</roll>
            <roll min="7" max="9">You make yourself extra flat against the ground and avoid anything terrible.</roll>
            <roll min="10" max="+">You will never stop running from what you saw. GAin +1 permanent movement.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Pit" number="26">
        <text>The ground bneath the event revealer's feet gives way and they plummet into a pit below. The event revealer rolls 1d10.&#xD;&#xA;If another survivor has a whp, they throw you a line in time; do not roll on the table.&#xD;&#xA;If the event revealer has the Tumble fighting art, they nimbly catch a ledge and haul themselves up; gain +1 speed token and do not roll on the table.</text>
        <rolltable person="Event Revealer">
            <roll min="1" max="1">You land with a sickening crunch, mangling your legs. Suffer the broken leg severe injury twice.</roll>
            <roll min="2" max="3">Your leg breaks your fall. Suffer the broken leg severe injury.</roll>
            <roll min="4" max="6">You land at the bottom with a loud thud. Suffer 2 event damage to a random hit location and archive all fragil gear in your gear grid.</roll>
            <roll min="7" max="9">You land at the bottom with a soft thud. Suffer 1 event damage to a random hit lcoation.</roll>
            <roll min="10" max="+">You manage to grab the edge of the pit and escape unharmed.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Man-Stealers" number="27">
        <text>Exhausted, the survivors rest. During their fitful sleep, a small insect approaches undetected. Choose 1 random male survivor and roll on the table. If there are no male survivors, nothing happens.&#xD;&#xA;If the chosen survivor has the Unconscious Fighter fighting art, they crush the bug while still snoring; do not roll on the table. They wake, confused, with random vermin resource in their hands.</text>
        <rolltable person="Random Male Survivor">
            <roll min="1" max="5">When you wake, your genitals have been stolen. In their place is nothing but smooth skin. Suffer the destroyed genitals severe injury.</roll>
            <roll min="6" max="+">You wake with a start, terrified to find menacing pincers approaching. Your defenses are quick. Without thinking, you wallop the insect craling on your pants, suffering 1 event damage to the waist.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Trollbird" number="28">
        <text>A rumpled, unsightly bird stands in the survivor's path. Its beady, wet eyes blink expectantly and it calls out with an eerie human chuckle. The survivors may archive 1 consumable item or gear, offering it to the trollbird. If any survivor is insane, they must feed the trollbird, if able. If they feed the trollbird, it hops off with a terrible cackle.&#xD;&#xA;If they don't feed the trollbird, it follows the survivors on their hunt, constantly mocking them with its chuckle. Roll 1d10. If any survivor has the Coprolalia disorder, they curse at the bird and make vigorous and vulgar gestures. The bird is impressed. Add +3 to your roll.</text>
        <rolltable person="Event Revealer">
            <roll min="1" max="5">The trollbird makes a terrible racket, alerting the monster. All survivors gain +1 understanding. At the start of the showdown, the monster ambushes the survivors.</roll>
            <roll min="6" max="+">The trollbird mocks and distracts the monster as teh survivors sneak up. All survivors gain +1 insanity. At the start of the showdown, the survivors ambush teh monster.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Dark Blacksmith" number="29">
        <text>The survivors cross paths with a tall, unnaturally thin man in a hooded robe. Where his feet strike the ground, sparks illuminate his path.&#xD;&#xA;Each survivor with 3+ courage may give him one piece of gear from their gear grid and roll on the table. If they have the Honoralbe disorder, add +3 to their roll.</text>
        <rolltable person="Any Survivor with 3+ courage">
            <roll min="1" max="2">The creature raises the object to its mouth and eats it. It's gone. Archive the gear card.</roll>
            <roll min="3" max="6">The creature refuses the gear and stares at you with a single, large eye. Suffer 1d10 brain event damage.</roll>
            <roll min="7" max="8">The creature unhinges its jaw and eats the piece of gear. In return, it hands you a shining shield. Gain the steel shield rare gear.</roll>
            <roll min="9" max="+">The creature unhinges its jaw and eats the piece of gear. In return, it hands you a shining sword. Gain the Steel Sword rare gear.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Rotten Faces" number="30">
        <text>The stone faces start to give under the survivor's feet. They are bloated and smell terrible. Each survivor rolls 1d10.</text>
        <rolltable person="Each survivor">
            <roll min="1" max="1">Your foot gets stuck and you quickly begin to sink into the ground. After a struggle you manage to break free. If you had leg armor, it is lost in the muck. Spend 3 survival or archive the gear.</roll>
            <roll min="2" max="5">Mired, you struggle to break free! Roll again on this table or spend 1 survival to escape.</roll>
            <roll min="6" max="9">You escape without incident.</roll>
            <roll min="10" max="+">You find something gross drudging through the rot! Gain 1 random basic resource.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Strange Path" number="31">
        <text>The survivors stop at the head of a path. Small lanterns twinkle, marking its edges.&#xD;&#xA;The event revealer decides whether or not the survivors follow the path. If the event revealer is insane, they must. If the survivors follow the path, they event revealer gains +1 understanding then rolls 1d10 and adds their understanding.&#xD;&#xA;Otherwise, roll again on the hunt event table before moving on the hunt board.</text>
        <rolltable person="Event Revealer">
            <roll min="1" max="1">A colossal finger descends from above, crushing a random survivor. They suffer 2 event damage to every hit location.</roll>
            <roll min="2" max="4">A random survivor tears off hysterically along a branch in the path. They return hours later, ghostly pale and with no recollection of what happened. They lose 1d10 survival.</roll>
            <roll min="5" max="7">The path twists and turns dizzyingly into the dark. All survivors suffer 1 brain event damage and the event revealer rolls again on this table, adding +2 to their roll.</roll>
            <roll min="8" max="9">The path leads the survivors to a large stone face with lanterns for eyes. Inside its open mouth is bounty. Each survivor gains 1 random basic resource.</roll>
            <roll min="10" max="+">The path leads to the beast you are hunting! the survivors ambush the monster. If any survivor has the Honorable disorder, they realize the folly of their ways and may remove the disorder. If any survivors remain Honorable, they announce their presence to the monster; the monster ambushes the survivors instead.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Sudden Madness" number="32" >
        <text>The event revealer is devastated by a piercing cacophony in thei head Roll 1d10. If the result is les then or equal to their current insanity, they go mad, lashing out at their compatriots! Each other survivor suffers 1 event damage to a random hit location before the event revealer regains control of themselves. if the even revealer has the Crazed fighting art, they gain insight from theri ordeal. Gain +10 insanity and +2 understanding</text>
    </event>
    <event name="It whispers your name" number="33" >
        <text>The event revealer trips over a protruding nose in the ground. The lips of stone face begin to move! it eh event reavealer has no name, the lips stop moving and nothing else happens. Otherwise, the lips seductively whisper the survvor's name. if the event revealer is insane, they are drawn in, savagely kissing the face. Repulsed and outraged, the other survivors suffer 1 brain even damage before pulling the crazed survivor from the ground and moving on. If the event revealer is not insance, they gain +1 understanding feeling on the custp of learning something. if any survivor has the Marrow Hunger impairment the face secretly whispers their life's purpose. They gain +1 permanent strength . Add the Murder settlement event to the timeline next year.</text>
    </event>
    <event name="Crippling Misery" number="34" >
        <text>Each survivor rolls 1d10. The lowest-scoring survivor (or survivors, in case of ties) becomes a straggler. if any survivor (or survivors) has teh Anxiety disorder, they are the straggler. Do not roll. The straggler is lost in a moment of profound self doubt. They slip, not having the will to catch themselves, and tumble off a steep hill of stone faces. They land awkwardly with a crunch, suffering the broken leg severe injury. Sobbing to themselves, they come to grips with just how terrible their life is and gain +1 understanding. If the straggler has Binge Eating Disorder, they wipe away their tears and reach out to a nearby critter, instinctually cramming it into their mouth for comfort Draw 1 random vermin resource and consume it</text>
    </event>
    <event name="Broken Lantern Oven" number="35" >
        <text>The survivors come across the shattered ruins of a small settlement. Ashen corpses dot the ruins, disintegration at the slightest touch. An extinguished lantern oven stands intact at the center of the settlement. The event revealer rolls 1d10 and adds their understanding. if the result is 5+ gain the Lantern Oven innovation. if the settlement already has this innovation, the event revealer harvests a broken lantern basic resouce from the remains. if the settlement has Song of the Brave, the group may nominate a brave survivor to Investigate the ruins of the settlements lantern hoard. They gain +1 courage and roll 1d10</text>
        <rolltable person= "Nominated Survivor">
            <roll min="1" max="5">You try to enter the ruined lantern hoard, but you are overcome with fear, kneeling over and comiting everywhere. When you rise, you find yourself physically incapable of pushing forward anymore. Gain the Apathetic disorder. </roll>
            <roll min="6" max="+">You are repelled by the ruined lantern hoard, but linger just long enough to grad a pair of insects scurrying within it. That;s as close as you're comfortable going. Gain 2 vermin resources of your choice. </roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="On the Trail" number="36" >
        <text>The survivors rush forward, feeling their quarry close at hand. Skip the next hunt space. if this movement begins the showdown, the survivors ambush their quarry. if any survivor has noisy gear, the survivors do not ambush, Start the showdown normally.</text>
    </event>
    <event name="Lost" number="37" >
        <text>The survivors are hopelessly lost in the unbroken darkness. Move the survivors 2 spaces back on the hunt board</text>
    </event>
    <event name="Gregalope" number="38" >
        <text>A massive Gregalope stands astride the horizon, its ancient body bloadted with tumors and scar tissue. its milky eyes catch sight of the survivors and it bounds away. Driven by a sudden desire, the survivors give chase. The event revealer rolls 1d10 and adds their movement to their roll. if any survivor has the Strategist fighting art, thye may corner the Gregalope at a giant stone face instead of giving chase. if they do, end the hunt imeadiately. Start a showdown with a level 2 Screaming Antelope, using its setup rules. in addition, place a Giant Stone Face adjacent to the monster and give the monster the Butcher's Berserker trait card. if the survivors prevail, gain the normal showdown rewards and 3 additional Screaming Antelope resources. </text>
        <rolltable person= "Event Revealer">
            <roll min="1" max="6">The survivors quickly fall behind the majestic beast. Move 1 space away from the quarry on the hunt board.</roll>
            <roll min="7" max="14">The Gregalope is far too fast. It's gone before you know it.</roll>
            <roll min="15" max="16">The survivor's lose sight of the Gregalope but discover a hidden path. You may re-roll the next result on the hunt even table.</roll>
            <roll min="17" max="+">Just before it leaps out of view. The Gregalope bows its mighty horns. The experiance changes the exhausted event revealer. They gain +1 permanent movement.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Heavy Mist" number="39" >
        <text>A heavy mist envelops the survivors, obscuring the lantern light. Roll 1d10. If the result is even, the survivors stumble in the right direction. if the result is odd, they get turned around; roll again on the hunt event table before moving on the hunt event board. if the showdown begins in the next space on the hunt board. the monster ambushes the survivors. </text>
    </event>
    <event name="Dream" number="40" >
        <text>The event revealed dreams of the upcoming hunt. They stand before the great beast, weapons ready, but it strikes them down. If the event revealer has 3+ courage. or if any survivor is a savior. the event revealer is emboldened by the dream and gains +1 evasion token. Otherwise the dream is merely rattling. Suffer 1 brain event damage. If any survivor has the Twilight Sword, they dream of indiscriminate slaughter. Add the Murder settlement event to the timeline 1d5 years from now.</text>
    </event>
    <event name="Nightmare" number="41" >
        <text>The event revealer dreams of teh upcoming hunt. The great beast vanishes during their battle and secretly follows them back to the settlement. They helplessly watch as it devours all they know and love. The event revealer gains +1d10 insanity insanity and -1 evasion token. If the settlement has a savior, they appear in the dream and defend their home. The event revealer gains +1d5 survival. if no survivor in the settlement or hunting party has a Twilight Sword, the event revealer envisions a maniacal version of themselves wielding the blade and gleefully slaughtering the beast. They awake to find a Twighlight Sword at there side, humming gently against their body. Instinctively the survivor recognizes the weight of the weapons curse and the promise of its power. The event revealer gains the Twiilight Sword as their weapon proficientcy type and gain +1 weapon with this weapon.</text>
    </event>
    <event name="Surgeon" number="42" >
        <text>A creaky carriage approaches the survivors. Richly appointed in red and gold. The carriage os carved on every side with lurid faces. A massive, twitching eye adorns the front, while the door of the carriage is a waiting, open mouth. Out of a small window, a snarled hanf beckons. One survivor with 3+ courage may choose to enter the wagon. They remove one impairment of sever injury and gain 1 random disorder. </text>
    </event>
    <event name="Fresh Kill" number="43" >
        <text>A carpet of skittering bugs points eh survivors to a freshly killed monster. The scavenging insects try to defend their sinner, but the survivors fight them off to claim the prixe. Each survivor rolls 2d10 and adds their Hunt XP. The highest-scoring survivor (roll off in case of ties) slays the most vermin and wins the putrid prize for themselves. They gain 1 random basic resource and 1 random vermon. </text>
    </event>
    <event name="Opportunists" number="44" >
        <text>While investigating their quarry's tracks, the survivors realize they are hunting not one, but two monsters. The two sets of tracks soon separate, leaving the event revealer to pick which tracks to follow. If they follow the larger tracks, conteinue hunting as normal. If they follow the samller tracks, start the showdown immediately. At the start of the showdown, the monster suffers 5 wounds. if the durvivors are victorious, they gain hald the basic resources and half the monster resources (rouned up) frp, rewards in the aftermath. </text>
    </event>
    <event name="Jagged Valley" number="45" >
        <text>A valley of sharp, white stones opens before the survivors, looking just like a toothy maw. As the survivors push and climb through the jagged spires, thye find that even the shallowest nick bleeds profusely. Each survivor suffers 1 event damage to the body. Unless a survivor has bandages to patch up their wounds, all survivors also gain 2 bleeding tokens! If any survivor has a pickaxe they may try to convince the other survivor s to let them investigate a bit more. If they are convinced roll 1d10.</text>
        <rolltable person="Survivor with a pickaxe" >
            <roll min="1" max="1">The white stones are teeth and teh survivors are in a giant mouth! Everyone must spend 1 survival to scamper out of the mouth. Anyone remaining inside is chewed to a pulp Dead. Do not gain the benefits of cannibalize.</roll>
            <roll min="2" max="5">The white stone is extremely hard. When the survivors finally break through, a horde of bugs scuttle forth from the holes. Gain 1 Hissing Cochroach vermin resouce. The excavaion was time consuming; roll again on the hunt event table before moving on the hunt board. </roll>
            <roll min="6" max="+">The survivores find a crack and expand it. Within is a hidden cache! Gain 1 Iron strange resource and 1 hissing cochroach vermin resource. The excavation was time consuming; roll again on the hunt event table before moving on the hunt board. </roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="River" number="46" >
        <text>The survivors come to the edge of a river of blood. Non-insane survivors suffer 1 brain event damage at teh sight of it. The survivors must investigate in order to pick up their quarry's trail Each survivor rulls 1d10. If no survivor successfully finds the monter's trail roll again on the hunt event table before moving on the hunt board</text>
        <rolltable person="Each Survivor" >
            <roll min="1" max="2">You lose your balence and fall into the river of blood! Instantly, a massive parasite crams its way down your throat, savagin your insides on the way in. suffer the broken rib sever body injury. You hope that that's all the parasite does to you. </roll>
            <roll min="3" max="5">Your quarry has defecated in the blood. Suffer 1 event damage to a random hit location from sifting through the fecal blood water too long.</roll>
            <roll min="6" max="8">You realise that the blood river is filled with the bloatd corpses of unrecognizable monsters. You feel compelled to fish some out! Gain 1 random basic resource. If you are wearing heavy gear, you fall in and swallow blood and soft,bloated monster bits. Reduce your survival to 1.</roll>
            <roll min="9" max="+">You successfully find the monster's trail</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Banquet Trees" number="47" >
        <text>A small copse of trees rises over an otherwise lifeless plain. Enticing red fruit hangs from the branches. Each survivor must spend 1 survival to resist the temptation to consume the fruit. Insane survivors and survivors with Binge Eating disorder must consume. If any survivor has a sickle they arve a line across the tree, drawing blood! The fuirt instantl sours. End this event. All survivors who consume the fruit roll 1d10</text>
        <rolltable person="Any survivor - Consome" >
            <roll min="1" max="5"> The addictive fruit savages your insides. Lose 1 survival and roll again on this table. If you had no survival, suffer 2 event damage to a random hit location</roll>
            <roll min="6" max="+"> You belch loudly in satisfaction and walk away. </roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Death Wager" number="48" >
        <text>The survivors are awoken by a traveler hidden in a deep cloak. The traveler pulls back its hood and reveals a deformed face with two chins curving away from each other each with its own grinning mouth. in a dreamlike state, the survivors all understand this entity is known as The Gambler and if they speak they will die. Until this event is completed, only the event revealer may speak. if any other player speaks, their survivor turns cold. Dead. The survivors must play The Gambler's game or be trapped with him forever. Each survivor rolls 1d10. </text>
        <rolltable person="Each Survivor" >
            <roll min="1" max="1">The Gambler reaches out and scoops up your dice. As they vanish within a fold of his cloak, you feel all traces of air leave your lungs and are unable to draw breath, Dead. </roll>
            <roll min="2" max="9">You do not lose, nor do you win. Play again if you wish, if you do. roll again on this table. </roll>
            <roll min="10" max="+">You win, Gain +1 permanent luck </roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Pus Fields" number="49" >
        <text>The landscape is dotted with large, swelling mounds oozing pus. The smallest jostle threatens to explode them. The survivors may carefully tread through the mounds or rush through. Carefully tread: you make it through without incident, but your progress is slowed. Roll again on the hunt event table before moving on the hunt board. Rush through: Each survivors rolls 1d10 and adds their evasion to the result. On a 7 or less they detonate one of the pus mounds! They suffer 2 event damage to a random hit location and become stinky for the rest of the lantern year. </text>
    </event>
    <event name="Gibbet" number="50" >
        <text>A crude iron cage swings from the branches of a massive tree. As the survivors approach, a man calls out to them from the cage, pleading to be freed. The survivors may pas him by and suffer 1 brain event damage as the prisoner weeps and pleads. If the survivors choose to free him the event reavealer rolls 1d10</text>
        <rolltable person="Event Revealer" >
            <roll min="1" max="1"> The survivors open the cage but all they find inside is a skeleton. All survivors suffer 2 brain event damage. </roll>
            <roll min="2" max="7"> The prisoner is thankful and follows the survivors until they rest. When they wake, each survivor loses 1 random resource (if they had any)</roll>
            <roll min="8" max="+"> The prisoner is grateful and follows the survivors home after the showdown. They settlement gains +1 population.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Refugees" number="51" >
        <text> The survivors encounter a group of fleeing settlers. If the settlement has Symposium and Language, the survivors manage to crudely communicate. The survivors may offer a resource or gear to help the distressed refugees. If they do, archive the offering. The refugees franticaly share their mournful tale. While much is lost in translation. they relate the savage incasion of a monster that destroyed their homae. The tale prepares the survivors for what lies ahead. At the start of the showdown, reveal the top 5 AI cards of the AI deck and put them back in any order. If any survivor has the Leader fighting art, one of the settlers is drawn to their charisma. Gain +1 population.</text>
    </event>
    <event name="Madflies" number="52" >
        <text> Tiny, persistent insects swarm the survivors, flying into their ears and nostrils. The bugs buzz maddeningly in their heads growing louder as they nest. Each survivors rolls 1d10</text>
        <rolltable person="Each survivor" >
            <roll min="1" max="2"> You dive into a nearby marsh to flush out the disgusting insects. It works, but now you're constantly distracted by the tiny bug corpses you occasionally hack up. Gain -1 evasion token. </roll>
            <roll min="3" max="7"> The buzzing immeadiately stops and the flies depart. Their rejection makes you feel strangely despondant. Gain +1 insanity</roll>
            <roll min="8" max="+"> Their eggs gestate incredibly quickly and madflies explode forth from your mouth! The experiance is gruesome, but makes you feel so alive! suffer the frenzy brain trauma. if you have the Rageholic disorder or Berserker fighting art, give birth to disgusting new life kindles your rage. Suffer the frenzy brain trauma again. </roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Mask Salesman" number="53" >
        <text>The survivors meet a trsaveling Mask Salesman on the road. He insists that he has special wares to offer. Shuffle on copy of each mask gear from the Mask Maker settlement location and draw one at random. The salesman is offering this mask. The event revealer rolls 1d10 to determine the price, Then gains the mask</text>
        <rolltable person="Event Revealer" >
            <roll min="1" max="3"> The salesman silently points at you. You instinctly hand him his asking price in exchange for the mask. Archive 1 gear of your choice from your gear grid and lose all survival </roll>
            <roll min="4" max="7"> The salesman slowly gestures for an offering. Archive 1 gear of your choice from your gear grid.</roll>
            <roll min="8" max="+"> As he imparts the mask to you, the salesman's lips form the sound of your name. It is gone. Give your survivor a new name(it must be different) and +1 survival for naming your survivor.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Bone Storm" number="54" >
        <text> Mighty winds tear across the landscape and skeletal remains. The survivors huddle together on the outskirts of the storm. They may either brave the storm or wait it out. Brave the storm: all survivors gain +1 courage and suffer 1 event damage to 3 random hit locations. Archive all fragile gear. Wait it out: roll twice on the hunt event table before moving on the hunt board</text>
    </event>
    <event name="Mudslide" number="55" >
        <text>A flash mudslide sweeps the survivors away. Each survivor rolls 1d10. if any survivors has a whip, they catch it around a pillar shaped bone and swing to safety: they do not roll.</text>
        <rolltable person="Each Survivor" >
            <roll min="1" max="2"> You're violently swept along, drowning in mud. Suffer 2 event damage to a random hit location and archive all fragile and soluble gear in your gear grid. Roll again on the table </roll>
            <roll min="3" max="7"> You manage to scramble free, but not before taking a serious beating. Suffer 2 event damage to your boday and archive all fragile and soluble gear in your gear grid.</roll>
            <roll min="8" max="9"> You reach higher ground. you're cakes in mud but otherwise unscathed.</roll>
            <roll min="10" max="+"> You remember being pulled under, the sensation of mud forcing itself down your throat, then nothing else. After the mudslide passes, the other survivors find you unharmed. Gain +1 insanity. </roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Dead Monster" number="56" >
        <text>The survivors find a decomposed monster corpse. It's too rotten to yield any resources. If any survivor has 3+ understanding , the survivors cover themselves in the dead monster's spilled blood. The stench will help them sneak up on their quarry. When the showdown starts, the survivors ambush the monster. If any survivors has the Squeamish disorder, they refuse to soil themselves. Do not ambush the monster If no survivor has 3+ understanding, the starving survivors feast on the rotting corpse. immediately losing control of their twisting guts. Each survivor loses 1 survival and cannot consume for the rest of the lantern year.</text>
    </event>
    <event name="Gorm's Laughter" number="57" >
        <text>The rhythmic wall of a Gorm's laughter reaches the survivors. filling them with fear. The cackling follows the survivors, tormenting them until they reach their quarry. Place a token on every hunt board space between the survivors and their quarry. When the survivors move into a space with a token, remove it and all non-deaf survivors suffer 1 brain event damage.</text>
    </event>
    <event name="Scent on the Wind" number="58" >
        <text>A strong wind blows, bringing with it the scents of distant places and things. The event revealer rolls 1d10.</text>
        <rolltable person="Event Revealer" >
            <roll min="1" max="5">The monster catches your scent. It moves one space closer. If this movement starts the showdown, the monster ambushes the survivors. </roll>
            <roll min="6" max="+">The survivors smell their quarry's foul odor and surge forward. The survivors may skip the next hunt space. If the movement starts the showdown, the survivors ambush the monster. </roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Signs of Battle" number="59" >
        <text>The survivors come upon the remains of a terrible battle between their quarry  and some unknown foe. The event may choose to investigate. If they do, gain +1 courage and roll 1d10. Otherwise, roll again on the hunt event table before moving on the hunt board.</text>
        <rolltable person="Event Revealer" >
            <roll min="1" max="2">The monster springs out of the dark, taking advantage of the distracted survivors. The monster ambushes the survivors. During showdown setup, place the event revealer directly in front of the monster. </roll>
            <roll min="3" max="7">The remains are human. The distraught and enraged survivors each suffer 1 brain event damage. If the settlement has Graves, they bury the dead and each survivor gains +1 survival. If the settlement has Cannibalize, gain 1 random basic resource. </roll>
            <roll min="8" max="+">The quarry has left the remains of another monster in its wake. Gain 1 random basic resource. </roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Wildfire" number="60" >
        <text>A massive wall of flame obstructs the survivors, incinerating the ground. It has destroyed whatever awaited the survivors and left chaos in its wake. Archive all hunt event cards in the next 2 hunt spaces. Place two basic hunt event cards in those spaces.</text>
    </event>
    <event name="Frozen Lightning" number="61" >
        <text>A storm over the survivors. Deep purple lightning flashes overhead. The bolts freeze in mid-strike and rain down on the survivors as jagged, glowing spikes. Each survivors rolls 1d10. The lowest scoring survivor (or survivors, in case of ties) becomes a straggler. A bolt crashes beside the straggler, catching  them in an explosion of razor-sharp crystals. They suffer 1d5 event damage to 2 random hit locations. Archive all fragile gear in the gear grid.</text>
    </event>
    <event name="Space Between the Rocks" number="62" >
        <text>The survivors are distracted by a dark crack in the endless sea of stone faces. If any survivor has a pickaxe, they strike the ground, causing the crack to expand into a gaping hole. Bravely reaching inside the survivor produces a blackened, twisted hunk. Gain 1 iron storage resource. Otherwise, each survivor rolls 1d10. The lowest scoring survivor (or survivors, in case of ties) becomes a straggler. The straggler stops to gaze into the depths and refuses to stop staring. When the other survivors drag them away, they babble incoherently. Whatever they saw changed them forever; they gain 1 random disorder. If all the survivors end up as stragglers, no one ever pulls them away and they are lost. Dead. </text>
    </event>
    <event name="Feet" number="63" >
        <text>The stone faces ahead are replaced by an expanse of stone feet sprouting from the ground. The survivors walk sole-to-sole with the feet. If any survivor is insane. They are convinced they have reached the underside of the world. They clutch the ground for dear life, terrified of falling off. Their raucous terror slows the survivors and attracts unwanted attention. Roll once on the hunt event table for each insane survivor before moving on the hunt board. If any of these rolls result in feet, ignore it and re-roll. If all the survivors are insane, they fall off the underside of the world. The survivors are dead unless the settlement chose Survival of the Fittest. If they did, the survivors bite down hard on the feet. Their teeth grind against stone as they refuse to let go. At once, the feet shatter, revealing orginary stone faces beneath. Set all survivors' insanity to 0. Each survivor suffers the shattered jaw severe head injery. Do not roll any additional hunt events caused by Feet.</text>
    </event>
    <event name="Stone Fountain" number="64" >
        <text>Two cupped stone hands rise out of the ground. The hands hold clear, cold water that trickles through the stone fingers in a seemingly endless supply. Any survivor may consume from the fountain. if they do, gain +1 courage and roll 1d10. If no one consumes, roll again on the hunt event table before moving on the hunt board. </text>
        <rolltable person="Any Survivor-Consume" >
            <roll min="1" max="4">The water is clear until it enters your lips, where it suddenly turns to blood. You spit out the foul liquird and suffer monster level brain event damage. If you have the hemophobia disorder, you also suffer monster level event damage to the body as you vomit violently in disgust.</roll>
            <roll min="5" max="8">It's water. Refreshing. </roll>
            <roll min="9" max="+">The water is clean and pure, like none the survivor has ever tasted. Gain +1 survival. </roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Statue" number="65" >
        <text>Cresting a hill, the survivors find a statue of a man sitting on a throne. If any survivor has 5+ understanding, the survivors may ignore the statue and end this event. Otherwise each survivor rolls 1d10. The lowest scoring survivor (roll off in case of ties) becomes a straggler. The straggler is drawn to the statue, touching it gently. In an instant, they are gone, replaced by the man from the throne, now flesh and blood. The staggler sits in his place on the throne, stone mouth open in a silent yell. They are gone forever. Consider them dead, but do not apply Cannibalize death principle; there is not body. The man offers his thanks and joins the hunting party without any explanation. He is a new survivor with the straggler's gear, 2 random disorders, and 2 hunt Hunt XP. Shuffle all weapon specialization cards (including expansions, if any) and draw one. The survivor has 3 ranks of proficiency in that weapon type. They gain +1d10 survival, +1d10 insanity. Give him a name and +1 survival for being named. If the settlement has Memento Mori, the statue resembles a deceased survivor. Replace the straggler with the record sheet of a fallen survivor. Remove all of their sever injuries. Set their Hunt XP to 2 (they Age again, as this is a new lifetime). They gain +1d10 survival, +1d10 insanity. You may give them 5 ranks of proficiency in a random weapon type.</text>
    </event>
    <event name="Forbidden World" number="66" >
        <text>There is a great rush of air. A booming, inhuman voice declares a single word in an unknown language. For one instant, the survivors understand. All non-deaf survivors gain +1 understanding and suffer 1 brain event damage. If they are insane they also gain 1 random disorder.</text>
    </event>
    <event name="Saliva Pools" number="67" >
        <text>The ground ahead is pockmarked with pools filled with a gooey liquid. They bubble merrily and stink of digesting meat. As the survivors move between them, they are overcome by waves of nausea. If any survivor has a sickle, they slice a few leaves from a nerby plant and everyone uses them to plug their noses and mask the smell. All survivors gain +1 understanding. Otherwise, each survivor rolls 1d10. If the result is less than their survival they continue on. Otherwise, they vomit into a nearby pool, suffering 1 event damage to the body. Before their eyes, the pool greedily dissolves their vomit, they gain +1 understanding. If any survivor has 3+ understanding, they devise a way to use the pools. Each survivor may place one piece of gear in the pool. Archive the gear and gain the resources used to craft it (if any).</text>
    </event>
    <event name="A Familiar Face" number="68" >
        <text>If no survivor have died yet this campaign, ignore this event and roll again on the hunt event table before moving on the hunt board. Each survivor rolls 1d10. The lowest scoring survivor (or survivors, in case of ties) becomes a straggler. While examining the stone faces underfoot, the straggler recognizes the face of a fallen friend. Bittersweet memories reduce them to tears. Reduce their insanity to 0 and gain +1 understanding.</text>
    </event>
    <event name="Time Lapse" number="69" >
        <text>The glow of the survivors' lanterns blurs, forming trails of light behind them. If the settlement has fought a Pheonix, the group recognizes the phenomenon. All survivors gain +1 understanding. The event revealer rolls 1d10 on the table below. If any survivor has an hours ring, they may instead select a die result. </text>
        <rolltable person="Event Revealer" >
            <roll min="1" max="3">The survivors' bodies suddenly age. All survivors with less than 10 Hunt XP gain +3 Hunt XP. Do not gain the benefits of Age. Your bodies have physically aged, no practical experience has been learned. </roll>
            <roll min="3" max="9">The survivors' minds fill with alien memories. They are no longer just themselves. They walk differently and speak with strange accents. Give each survivor a new name and +1 survival for being names. Each survivor gains +1 Hunt XP and 1 random disorder. If your settlement has Survival of Fittest, and you've already used your once-per-lifetime reroll, you may use it again. </roll>
            <roll min="10" max="+">The survivors are suddenly standing by their quarry! Start the showdown immediately.  </roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Tomb of Excellence" number="70" >
        <text>The survivors find a serene, luxurious tomb, immaculate in its construction and condition. Elegant murals decorate the walls, depicting glorious victories over the very monster the survivors are hunting. The survivors are baffled by its presence. The event revealer investigates and rolls 1d10.</text>
        <rolltable person="Event revealer" type="Investigate" >
            <roll min="1" max="1">The survivors bemoan how eak they are compared to the warriors in the murals. All survivors lose 1 survival.</roll>
            <roll min="2" max="5">It's nice to see something pretty for once, eh?</roll>
            <roll min="6" max="9">The survivors can't remember ever feeling so cheerful and inspired. Each survivor gains +1 courage.</roll>
            <roll min="10" max="+">The doorway to the tomb is framed with a wood that has small hands for grain. Inside, murals depict a hero at the center of a labyrith that is holding a giant, human-filled fruit above his head. Each survivor gains +1 understanding. If the settlement has Pictographs, the survivors find information about their quarry. At the start of the showdown, they may place the monster's trap at the bottom of the hit location deck.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Found Relix" number="71" >
        <text>Amidst the endless stone faces, the event revealer notices an unusual object on the ground. The event revealer investigates and rolls 1d10.&#xD;&#xA;If the settlement has Records, add +6 to the result.</text>
        <rolltable person="Event revealer" type="Investigate" >
            <roll min="1" max="2">You find a weathered, purple stone with a swirling texture. It is shockingly heavy. Mesmerized by the stone, you hide it from the other survivors. Gain the Secretive disorder and -1 movement token from lugging the stone around.</roll>
            <roll min="3" max="4">Useless junk litters the ground.</roll>
            <roll min="5" max="9">You find a stone heart that pulses with warmth as you hold it in your hands. Gain +1 insanity.</roll>
            <roll min="10" max="+">You find a mask with living lips. If you return to the settlement with the mask, it quickly learns your language and shares its secrets before crumbling to dust. At the start of the next settlement phase, draw 3 innovations from the innovation deck and add one to your settlement at no cost.&#xD;If any survivor has a Final Lantern, it begins to flash and vibrate wildly. The mask disintegrates and all survivors suffer 1 brain event damage.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Something to Pass the Time" number="72" >
        <text>IF the settlement does not have Symposim, ignore this event and roll again on the hunt event table before moving on the hunt board. Otherwise, the event revealer suggests a word game to lighten the mood as the survivors trudge forward. The event revealer rolls 1d10. If the settlement has Song of the Brave, add +4 to your roll.</text>
        <rolltable person="Event revealer" >
            <roll min="1" max="2">The survivors' boisterous voices attract their quarry. The moster ambushes them.</roll>
            <roll min="3" max="7">No one else is in the mood for a game. The event revealer loses 1 courage.</roll>
            <roll min="8" max="9">The survivors play the simple but entertaining game. Each survivor gains +1 courage.</roll>
            <roll min="10" max="+">The game is astonishingly fun and the survivors' spirits soar with their booming laughter. Each survivor rolls 1d10. On a 6+, they gain 1 survivoal or cure 1 disorder.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Golden Ember" number="73" >
        <text>The way forward is blocked by a dense, gold-flecked smoke. If the survivors have a Final Lantern, it guides them through the smoke without any trouble; end this event.&#xD;&#xA;The survivors may push ahead and brave the smoke. If they do, each survivor gains +1 courageand the event revealer rolls 1d10. If they don't brave the smoke, they take the long way around; roll again on teh huntevent table before moving on the hunt board.&#xD;&#xA;The survivors carefully descend into the crater, finding the ruins of a settlement surrounded by a ring of skulls. The settlement is absolutely demolished and almost everything has been ground to powder from some tremendous force. The skulls face away from the ruins and in each gaping mouth, a golden ember spews smoke.&#xD;&#xA;The sight is haunting; each survivors suffers 1d10 brain event damage and gains 1 random disorder. The survivors gingerly sift through the ruins. Nominate a survivor to investigate and roll 1d10.</text>
        <rolltable person="Event revealer" >
            <roll min="1" max="5">The smoke overwhelms the survivors. As they run through the glittering smog, each survivor suffers 1 event damage to the head and chest locations. When they finally breach the haze's end, they silently walk on. No one is comforatable sharing the terrible things they glimpsed. Each survivor gains 1 random disorder.</roll>
            <roll min="6" max="+">The survivors grasp each other's hands, from a line, and traverse the smoke. They breathe through rags and take turns peeking out for orientation. Somewhere, deep within the smoke, they stumble across a crater. They may ignore it and escape the smoke (ending this event_ or explore the crater</roll>
        </rolltable>
        <rolltable person="Nominated survivor" type="Investigate">
            <roll min="1" max="1">Against all reason, you feel compelled to reach into a skull and take an ember. Your flesh sizzles, blinding you with pain and yet you cannot stop yourself from reaching for your oun mouth. If you have a broken jaw, you're twarted. You drop the golden ember from your burning hand. Suffer the dismembered arm severe injury. Shaken, the survivors flee the smoke. Otherwise, your jaw clamps shut around the ember, the flesh of your mouth melts shut, muffling your cries of pain. Smoke pours from your eyes, nose, and ears. If the settlement has Survival of the Fittest, the urge to live wins out and you savagely break open your own jaw, Suffer the broken jaw severe head injury. The ember tumbles tot he ground, its sputtering hiss rining in your ears as all survivors flee in horror. Otherwise, your smoking, melting body marches robotically into the ring of skulls, laying itself in the place of the disturbed skull. The putrid smell of your burning brain suffuses the smoke in the air. The sight is so disturbing that all other suvivors flee, never to speak of what happened.</roll>
            <roll min="2" max="4">You sense the extremem danger from the golden embers you linger just long enough to grab a small trinkey. Gain 1 Broken Lantern basic resource.</roll>
            <roll min="5" max="8">You notice that the settlement is strewn with lanterns, all extinguished and smashed nearly beyond recognition. The survivors resolve that this will never happen to them. If any survivor returns to the settlement this year, gain +2 endeavors.</roll>
            <roll min="9" max="+">Amidst the runs, you find only one unbroken object. A Twilight Sword. It rests, respectfully laid across a mostly undamaged survivors skeleton. IF the settlement does not have a Twilight Sword, and no survivor in the group has the Honorable disorder, you may nominate a survivor to gain the Twilight Sword rare gear. If you do and the Hodded Knight story event is not on the timeline, add it to the timeline 2 years from now.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Antler-Gouged" number="74" >
        <text>A great battle for dominance between two enormous antelopes has left the stone-faced ground gouged with crisscrossing scars. Each survivor rolls 1d10.</text>
        <rolltable person="Each survivor" >
            <roll min="1" max="2">You trip over the jagged ground and shred your flesh! Suffer the torn muscle severe leg injury.</roll>
            <roll min="3" max="8">You carefully tread over the destroyed faces.</roll>
            <roll min="9" max="+">You find a loosened stone. Gain a Founding Stone starting gear.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Oops!" number="75" >
        <text>Stumbling through the darkness, the event revealer crashes into the ground, crushing their lantern beneath them. The living light inside the lantern becomes agitaged by the survivor's clumsiness and burns a piece of gear. The event revealer archives 1 gear of their choice from their gear grid.</text>
    </event>
    <event name="Dream the Way" number="76" >
        <text>The survivors have vivd, fevered vision of what lies ahead. All at once, they are startled awake and frantically compare the horrors they saw.&#xD;&#xA;Each survivor rolls 1d10. If any survivors is a savior, their powerful dream envelopes the group; each survivor may select whatever die roll result they want. If any survivors' rolls are the smae, theose survivors discover they had the exact same dream. They gain +1 insanity. If any duplicate rolls are 1-s, the event revealer may re-roll any one roll result this hunt phase (any one die roll, not just their roll).</text>
    </event>
    <event name="Sinkhole" number="77" >
        <text>A gaping sinkhole suddenly opens under the survivors, revealing a swirling black pool of ichor beneath them. Each survivor rolls 1d10. The lowest scoring survivor (or survivors, in case of ties) becomes a straggler.&#xD;&#xA;Each straggler rolls 1d10. If any other survivor has a whip, they throw a line to the straggler. Each straggler adds +4 to their roll.</text>
        <rolltable person="Straggler" >
            <roll min="1" max="1">You are swallowed by the sinkhole, moments later it regurgitates you completely naked. Your gear is hopelessly lost in the miasma. Archive all gear in your gear grid.</roll>
            <roll min="2" max="4">The other survivors haul you up, but not before something is sucked below the surface. Archive 1 gear of your choice from your gear grid.</roll>
            <roll min="5" max="9">You are dragged to safety, terrified but unharmed.</roll>
            <roll min="10" max="+">After a monumental effort, the other survivors pull you free. Someone is clinging tightly to your feet (+1 population)! As they retreat to your settlement, each survivor suffers 1 brain event damage.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Dead Great Game Hunter" number="78" >
        <text>The survivors find a corpse dressed in brightly-colored clothing, clutching something to its chest. The event revealer may investigate. If they do, they gain +1 courage and roll 1d10. If any survivor has a whip, they lash the corpse from afar; add +4 to your roll.&#xD;&#xA;Otherwise, roll again on the hunt event table before moving on the hunt board.</text>
        <rolltable person="Event revealer" type="Investigate" >
            <roll min="1" max="1">He was holding an explosive! Moving it causes it to detonate, blowing off your hand. Suffer the dismembered arm severe arm injury.</roll>
            <roll min="2" max="4">He was holding an explosive! It explodes, but you pull away before disaster strikes. Gain -1 accuracy token.</roll>
            <roll min="5" max="9">His hands are empty. If the settlement has Cannibalize, gain 1 random basic resource. If the settlement has Graves, gain +1 understanding.</roll>
            <roll min="10" max="+">His hands contain a jeweled bottle filled with a chartreuse liquid. Gain 1 Frenzy Drink gear.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Dying Small Prospector" number="79" >
        <text>If your settlement already has a Portcullis Key, the prospector is gone. Roll again on the hunt event table before moving on the hunt board.&#xD;&#xA;The survivors discover a body slumped against a large stone face. Moving closer, they find a small, dying prospector riddled with arrows. As they approach, he growls a warning, threatening them with a huge stone shard. When he sees that they are not evil monsters, he calms down and gives them a key. With his dying breath hea says: "This is the key to the portcullis. Without it, you will never get through"&#xD;&#xA;Record the Portcullis Key in the settlement record sheet notes.&#xD;&#xA;If the settlement has Graves, the event revealer builds a small monument of broken stone noses and gains +1 understanding.</text>
    </event>
    <event name="Lovelorn Rock" number="80" >
        <text>The survivors pass a ring of stones with an unassuming boulder at the center. Each survivor rolls 1d10. The lowest scoring survivor (randomize in case of ties) becomes a straggler.&#xD;&#xA;The straggler hefts the boulder (it's heavy!) and promises to carry it everywhere, forever in love. They amust always leave one space in their gear grid empty, as it contains their beloved rock. Record this on your survivor sheet. The rock can be lost or archived like other gear; if it is lost, the survivor mourns their beloved and reclaims the space in their gear grid.</text>
    </event>
    <event name="Field of Arms" number="81">
        <text>The survivors carefully tread along the back of a massive, sleeping monster. Instead of fur, it has elongated arms, several of them twitching to whatever dream the great beast is in the misdst of. The survivors don't disturb the monster's deep sleep and cross without issue.&#xD;&#xA;If any survivor has a sickle, they gingerly remove some tough skin from one of the arms and gain 1 Hide basic resource.</text>
    </event>
    <event name="Consuming Grass" number="82">
        <text>Vibrant green grass grows in patches ahead of the survivors. Closer inspection of the delicate leaves reveals they are as sharp as any blade. Each survivor rolls 1d10. They lowest scoring survivor (or survivors, in case of ties) becomes a straggler. As the survivors carefully pick their way past the verdant hazards, the straggler stumbles into the brush. They rolls 1d10..&#xD;&#xA;If any survivor has a whip, a hasty tether is made. Add +4 to your roll.</text>
        <rolltable person="Straggler">
            <roll min="1" max="1">You land in the grass patch. As you climb to your feet, you realize it's too late. The parts of your body that touched the ground have sprouted with sharp blades of grass. Any attempt to remove them only spreads them further over your body. During the showdown, you are never a threat (ignore any effect that would make you a threat, even the White Lion's Sniff). At the end of the showdown, your body blossoms inot a whorl of immaculate green grass. Dead.</roll>
            <roll min="2" max="9">You fall but manage to interpose something between the grass and your bare skin. Either archive 1 gear of your choice from your gear grid to protect yourself, or treat this result as if you rolled a 1.</roll>
            <roll min="10" max="+">You stop your fall before it's too late.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Flesh Monolith" number="83">
        <text>The survivors approach a 5-sided monolith made of flesh that stretches into the darkness overhead. Limbs and faces both human and bizarre protrude from all sides. The event revealer gains +1 courage and investigates.</text>
        <rolltable persone="Event revealer" type="Investigate">
            <roll min="1" max="1">The monolith's limbs spring to life, grabbing hold before you can react. They join your body parts to its own with maddening efficiency as you are ripped apart in a shower of gore. Dead. The horrible sight causes all other survivors to suffer 3 brain event damage and they all gain Post Traumatic Stress disorder. If the settlement has Survival of the Fittest, you fight the monolith! The horrible edifice tears your arm off, but you bite one of its appendages in return, severing it! The monolith retreats inot the ground as you roar in triumpth. Suffer the dismember arms evere injury and gain +1 permanent strength. All other survivors stand in awe and gain +3 insanity and +1 courage.</roll>
            <roll min="2" max="4">Hands and tentacles grasp at you. Spend 1 survival to wriggle away or treat this result as if you rolled a 1.</roll>
            <roll min="5" max="9">All survivors are driven back with horror. They all suffer quarry's monster level brain event damage.</roll>
            <roll min="10" max="+">As the survivors draw near, they discover that this flesh monolith is actually an enormous pile of survivors' corpses, many with badly broken limbs. The pile is covered in chunks of strange, sweet-smelling viscera.&#xD;If the settlement has Graves, you ascend the heap and find 3 barely living survivors, their bodies devoid of nourishment and their eyes too sensitive for lantern light. If you return to the settlement, +3 population. These new survivors cannot depart for 2 lantern years as they need time to recover (note this on the timeline).&#xD;Otherwise, all you manage to harvest from the pile of emaciated corpses is 2 Organ basic resources. Their skin is too soft and bones too brittle to be of any use.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
    <event name="Scribe's Book" number="84">
        <text>A huge, ornately bound book lays open before the survivors. If the settlement has Pictographs, any survivor with 3+ courage may write their name in the book. Insane survivors with 3+ courage must write.&#xD;&#xA;Each survivor who writes their name in the book rolls 1d10 and adds their understanding. If no one writes, roll again on the hunt event table before moving on the hunt board.</text>
        <rolltable person="Any sruvivor with 3+ courage">
            <roll min="1" max="4">As you finish writing your name, you know that you did something terribly wrong. You vanish from history. Dead. Archive your gear.</roll>
            <roll min="5" max="8">Nothing happens.</roll>
            <roll min="9" max="10">As you write your name, you feel restored. Heall all injury levels and lost armor points. Gain +2 survival.</roll>
            <roll min="11" max="14">You feel assured that as long as your name is in the book, nothing bad can happen to you. Gain two of the following: +2 courage, +2 understanding, or +2 survival.</roll>
            <roll min="15" max="+">The book proves the undeniable mark you leave on the world. Gain +1 survival, +1 understanding, +1 courage, +1 permanent speed, and +1 permanent strength.</roll>
        </rolltable>
    </event>
</huntevents>